Good morning, this is Dan Margolis filling in for Rabbi Lindzer while
he is unavailable, and today is the 24th of June, the 18th
of סיון, Sivan, and we are starting on כ"ג עמוד ב' Kaf
Gimmel Amud Bet with the first תא שמע Tashma about ten lines
down or so. The גמרא Gemara says: תא שמע שיסה בו את
הכלב שיסה בו את הנחש פטור. Tashma Shissa Bo et HaKelev Shissa
Bo et HaNachash Patur. So if a person entices, he sics their
dog on you or sics their snake on you, that is they
encourage someone else's animal to attack a third party. So פטור, Patur,
such a person is totally פטור. Patur. Why? Because we would think
either the owner is responsible
and that would make sense if the owner were the one responsible
for not taking care of the animal, and then we would also
think that the inciter should be liable because it's their responsibility for
having enticed the animal to attack. But because they're two different people,
that liability is kind of split between them. So we're going to...
so this is in the instance no one's responsible?
So that's what
the גמרא Gemara has to discuss. The גמרא Gemara has a question.
So מאן פטור? Man Patur? Who's going to be פטור? Patur? Now
the question is we had already been in the middle of discussing
the question of the fact that this is trying to refute the
notion that the mouth of an animal is considered רשות המזיק Reshut
HaMazik
כחצר המזיק. Kechatzer HaMazik. Because if the cow when it's eating your
food or the dog when it's biting someone, if the mouth is
considered the domain of...
I sent someone else down with the keys too. Yes but... Oh,
I'm sorry, no, okay, so then we'll be waiting in the lobby
as they come back up. So
that if the mouth of the animal is considered to be the
property of the מזיק, Mazik, the person causing the damage because it's
their animal, but then the problem will be that you would say,
okay, so then how can you ever be חייב Chayav for שן?
Shen? Because שן Shen you're פטור Patur in your own property. That
was the whole question. So the גמרא Gemara says: שיסה בו את
הכלב שיסה בו את הנחש פטור. Shissa Bo et HaKelev Shissa Bo
et HaNachash Patur. So מאן פטור? Man Patur? Who is the one
who is פטור? Patur? משסה פטור, Mashse Patur, the one who enticed
the animal to attack, וחייב בעל כלב, Vechayav Baal Kelev, and the
owner of the animal should be חייב Chayav because it was that
their animal who attacked. So obviously they should be חייב. Chayav. So
that says the גמרא Gemara since... Okay, אי אמר Ee amar כחצר
המזיק דמי, Kechatzer HaMazik dami, if you say that even if
you did a good שמירה? Shmira?
Well look, you had your dog in your yard, it was all
tied up, whatever, and then someone comes over and gets the dog
to bite someone, say here put your hand in his mouth, he's
really nice, and then they hit the dog or something. So that
would be in such a case, so here it sounds like you
didn't account for all the possibilities, the בעל הכלב Baal HaKelev is
חייב. Chayav. Now I don't know all the details exactly in terms
of the שמירה, Shmira, but that's how it
seems that you should be חייב. Chayav.
In other words, like what?
Look in the end it's
your animal, your animal caused damage, so that's the responsibility.
Okay, you're חייב חצי נזק? Chayav Chatzi Nezek?
No, it says in this case if the animal is a כלב,
Kelev, a כלב Kelev is מועד, Muad, no? So a כלב Kelev
should be נזק שלם. Nezek Shalem. כי מועדים? Ki muadim? Okay, ואי
אמר Ve-ee amar כחצר המזיק דמי, Kechatzer HaMazik dami, if we say
that the mouth of the animal is like the property of the
מזיק, Mazik, so לימא ליה מן בעא ידך בפומי דכלבאי? Leima leh
man ba yadecha befumei dekalbai?
Why did you put your hand in my dog's mouth? Meaning you
have no right to be in my property, if you go into
my property and you get damage... Were you able to get Rav
Steven his key in the end? Okay, good, thank you.
So why did you put your hand into my dog's mouth? If
you put your hand into your dog's mouth and that's why you
got damage, so it shouldn't be my responsibility that my dog bit
you. That was what Michael was saying. Okay, so אימא פטור אף
משסה. Ayma patur af mashse.
Maybe we should say obviously the owner is פטור Patur and even
the one who enticed the animal to bite as well.
So both should be... it should be פטורים Pturim then, not פטור.
Patur.
But it says אף פטור Af Patur meaning even the one who's
not obvious...
it means the גרסא Girsa is bad?
No, it doesn't mean the גרסא Girsa is bad. What it means
is that you have to read it as אף, Af, that is
obviously the owner of the animal is פטור Patur because why would
you put your hand in somebody else's dog's mouth? And even the
one who enticed the animal to attack is פטור Patur because that's
the less obvious case.
What about is
there any parallel to sending your arrow out in terms of the
lighting the אש Esh in the torch, shooting... sending the animal to
attack?
Except that an animal is obviously different than אש, Esh, right? We
say the whole point of אש Esh is that it's not a
conscious being in any sense, right?
Right, but I mean here he seems to be...
it's difficult to make that comparison...
he's directing that
force?
Yeah, maybe. We have a lot to cover today, that's the goal
so we'll see. Okay, ואי בעית אימא Ve-ee bayit ayma דאפקי לה
ניבי וסתרתיה. De-afke leh nivei vestarteh.
So maybe what did you do? You took the animal, right? And...
ניבי Nivei or שיני? Shinai?
Yeah,
the teeth, right? Oh, just the big... because the animal, meaning to
say that the dog should be חייב, Chayav, that the dog itself
is the only one who's חייב Chayav because in the end the
dog is the one who got... Got upset. Right?
What does סרטיה sartei mean?
That
I think that it's that the dog attacked, that is, the dog
bared its teeth and that was the reason that in such a
case the person who incited the animal,
meaning this is a way to say even that even if you
say כחצר המזיק, kechatzer hamazik, the owner is still that the owner
is פטור, patur, why? Because the... sorry, not the other way. That
the owner should be חייב chayav because in that because this is
איבעית אימא. iba'is eima. So איבעית אימא iba'is eima is to say
alternatively, totally alternatively שהוציא שיניו וסרטו דלא הכניס ידו לתוך פיו shehotzi
shinav vesarto delo hichnis yado letoch piv
that the dog opened its mouth to bite rather than the person
putting their hand into the dog's mouth, and in that sense with
an open mouth the dog's mouth is no longer like כחצר המזיק
kechatzer hamazik and therefore the owner would be חייב chayav because the
dog attacked as if in a position of outside of his property.
So again I'm not exactly sure where you draw the line between
an open mouth and a closed mouth dog bite, but that seems
to be what that איבעית אימא iba'is eima is suggesting. Let's see.
איבעית אימא דאפקלן ניביה iba'is eima de'afkalan niveiha he as if opened
his mouth, opened his teeth, וסרטיה vesartei and attacked and look at
what רש"י Rashi says שהוציא שיניו וסרטו דלא הכניס ידו לתוך פיו
shehotzi shinav vesarto delo hichnis yado letoch piv
that is the dog jumped out and attacked rather than that the
person put their hand into the dog's mouth.
Right, so then why... then that means someone should be חייב chayav
though.
Right, that means that the בעל הכלב ba'al hakelev should be חייב
chayav because the dog attacked outside of his חצר. chatzer. If the
whole פטור, patur, if the whole exemption was that the mouth of
the dog is considered to be the property of the מזיק, mazik,
so then if the dog attacks with an open mouth, that is
as if the teeth are no longer in the mouth,
then at that point the בעל הכלב ba'al hakelev would be חייב.
chayav.
But here in the איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, isn't it just a
different way of explaining the same ruling?
Exactly, that is even למאן דאמר le'man de'amar the mouth of the
dog is כחצר המזיק, kechatzer hamazik, nonetheless, one person is פטור, patur,
that is the שיסא shisa is פטור patur and the בעל ba'al
would be חייב chayav in that case. That's actually a מחלוקת machlokes
between the first way of reading the ברייתא braisa and the איבעית
אימא. iba'is eima. Okay. תא שמע. ta shma. השיך בו את הנחש.
hishich bo es hanachash. What if you get someone... get a snake
to bite someone else? You attack someone with a snake. Okay. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מחייב mechayev וחכמים vechachamim פוטרין. potrin. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says you're חייב chayav and חכמים chachamim say you're פטור. patur.
Why? ואמר רב אחא בר יעקב ve'amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
משיתמצי mishitamtzi לומר דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rabbi Yehuda ארס נחש בין
שיניו הוא עומד. eres nachash bein shinav hu omed. So maybe the
reason for רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's opinion is that he says that
the venom of a snake is in its teeth, that is ארס
נחש בין שיניו הוא עומד eres nachash bein shinav hu omed it's
standing in the fangs. Okay, therefore לפיכך lefichach מכיש machish בסייף besayaf
and the person, the owner of the snake, should be executed with
a sword, beheading, because it's הריגה. hariga. You committed murder because what
did you do? You took a snake which is a dangerous weapon
as if, it has the venom already in its teeth and and
bit into someone with the snake, and it's just a... it's as
if you injected someone with a poison. That is a snake already
has the venom in its fangs. ונחש פטור venachash patur and the...
that is the person who did the attack who took the snake
is חייב chayav because he murdered someone with a dangerous weapon and
the owner of the snake is פטור patur because in the end
it was an inevitable consequence. It wasn't anything he could do to
prevent the snake from biting. It was just part of how the
venom is... it's removed from the ownership of the animal. ודברי חכמים
vedivrei chachamim ארס נחש מעצמו מקיא. eres nachash me'atzmo makya.
According to חכמים, chachamim, the venom of the snake is expelled by
the snake's own will. The snake spits out its own venom according
to its making that decision. לפיכך lefichach נחש בסקילה nachash biskila and
therefore the person who attacked with the snake didn't know whether the
snake was actually going to spit out venom or not. So a
snake is never going to be ודאי vadai a lethal weapon and
therefore the only punishment in this case is that the animal, because
it's an animal who caused someone to die, the animal will die
by סקילה skila but the person who took the snake and bit
someone else with... there's no verb in English for this, to have
the snake to bite someone, that person would be פטור. patur. Okay,
so ומכיש פטור. umachish patur. So okay, ואי אמרת פי פרה כחצר
המזיק דמי, ve'ei amart pi parah kechatzer hamazik dami, if you say
that the mouth of the cow is like the property of the
מזיק, mazik, לימא ליה מאי בעיא ידך בפומי דחיוואי leima lei mai
ba'aya yadcha befumei dechivai
so why would you put your hand into my snake's mouth? That
is the same thing. That is again, even if you want to
say this whole discussion, to say that the owner of the snake
is חייב chayav according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who thinks that
the venom is lodged in the snake's fangs, that nonetheless would not
make sense according to the שיטה shita פי פרה כחצר המזיק דמי.
pi parah kechatzer hamazik dami. So לענין קטלא לא אמרינן. le'inyan katala
lo amrinan. We wouldn't know. So maybe the answer is that according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we don't say that in a case
of a capital crime. We only say that in by civil damages.
מאי טעמא דתניא הנכנס לחצר בעל הבית שלא ברשות ונגחו שורו של
בעל הבית. mai ta'ama detanya hanichnas lechatzer ba'al habayis shelo birshus venegacho
shoro shel ba'al habayis. So what about the case in the ברייתא?
baraita? A person goes into someone's חצר chatzer without permission and in
that חצר chatzer he gets gored by the ox and he dies.
So שורו של בעל הבית, shoro shel ba'al habayit, the ox is
owned by the property owner,
ומת, u-mes, and we know that the ruling in that case is
as exactly identical according to as חכמים שיטה, Chachamim's shita, that is
the animal gets executed by סקילה skila because it caused someone to
die, ובעלים פטורים u-be'alim pturim because why what were you doing in
my property that you got injured? So what do we say ובעלים
פטורים מן הכופר? u-be'alim pturim min ha-kofer? They're only פטור patur from
paying כופר, kofer, that is the special
cost that you have to pay if your animal, that is an
animal that was a תם, tam, killed someone. So that's the reason
why you say ובעלים פטורים מן הכופר. u-be'alim pturim min ha-kofer. So
the owner is פטור patur from paying כופר, kofer, not from any
crime at all. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? דאמר ליה ברשותי מאי בעית.
de-amar lei be-rishusi mai bayis. Why what were you doing in my
property? שורו נמי, shoro nami, so shouldn't we say that the animal
also should be as if the animal itself is פטור patur for
damaging in that case because why should why should the שור shor
be executed just because someone was doing in somebody else's property? ליה
ליה מאי בעית ברשותי. lei lei mai bayis be-rishusi. So he can
also say what were you doing in my in my חצר? chatzer?
אלא לעניין קטלא לא אמרינן. ella le-inyan katala lo amrinan. So and
we don't say we don't say that in other words for a
capital crime, that is the fact that the ox has to be
killed, we don't care whether it was that you were in their
property by permission or not. Okay. הנהו עיזי דבי תרבו. hanehu izi
de-vei tarbu. Yes sure.
This is so relevant to me to like about the נחש. nachash.
Yeah. You said would you really practically say according to חכמים Chachamim
that like the everyone gets the animal maybe gets whatever and you
can kill the animal but like everyone gets off? But nothing? I
can be doing this all day long?
You take a snake or you take a venomous snake and and
throw it at someone so that it bites onto their neck? And
and and it's and it's the snake's choice whether to inject the
venom or not? To a certain extent, yes, meaning meaning you can't
say that...
No but even if I put it right, I put it directly
on you, on this guy, until it kills him and no one...
But the snake, the snake in the end, according to the way
חכמים Chachamim understand it, I'm not an expert in in snake biology
enough to know which kinds of snakes operate in which ways, but
as far as I understand it most venomous snakes do not automatically
release their venom. That is they choose when to release the venom.
חכמים Chachamim had the right understanding of the מציאות. metzius. And so
if I make a snake bite you, it's never בודאי be-vadai
100% that that will be a lethal damage. So you can't make
me, you can't call me a murderer
for hitting you with the snake that maybe is going to kill
you and maybe's not. How can you execute me for that?
I'm not talking about execution.
Well that's exactly the question.
No but my question is like so practically I'm just I walk
I do that I walk...
No of course there are all other sorts of נזיקין nezikin involved,
but whether this is a capital crime, whether this is murder, the
answer is not murder.
So okay but then you say you still have to pay for
נזק? nezek? You have to pay for נזק? nezek?
I would assume with a strong assumption that you would have to
pay all sorts of נזיקין. nezikin. If you have a snake bite
even if it's not a lethal bite obviously you're חייב chayav to
pay.
Wait but what is this we call, but doesn't wouldn't wouldn't that
like would you still be responsible for נזק צער ריפוי שבת ובושת?
nezek tza'ar ripui sheves u-voshes? Well קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kim lei
be-drabba minei if
you had
to all other kinds of capital punishment. But it's not a murder
case because you
can't pay נזק nezek when you kill somebody if you're not liable
for his for for the for the death.
No because we have קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kim lei be-drabba minei.
So if it's a capital crime, okay, so this is going to
be a whole much larger, you want to write a שאלה sheila
to a real פוסק posek who can answer this question, fine. But
if you attack someone with a venomous snake, what kind of נזיקין
nezikin you have to pay, it's a good question. But at least
from this סוגיא, sugya, is it murder or not? The answer is
not murder because the snake gets, according to חכמים, Chachamim, because the
snake gets to choose whether to release the venom or not. Okay.
Because again, the snakes have to regrow their venom over time, so
that if they use it all up every time that they bite,
then they're going to run out of venom. Okay. So הנהו עיזי
דבי תרבו, hanehu izi de-vei tarbu, there were these goats from Beit
Tarbu, דהוו
מפסדי ליה לרב יוסף,
de-havu mafsedi lei
le-Rav Yosef, they were causing damage to Rav Yosef's property. אמר ליה
לאביי amar lei le-Abaye זיל אימא להו דליצנעינהו, zil eima le-hu de-litzne'inhu,
so go tell them that they have to lock 'em up. So
אמר ליה אמאי, amar lei amai, so he said why? איזיל דאי
אזלינהו, izil de-ee azlinhu, so they'll say you know like the goats
are going to go and do what they're going to do. Why
do you have to, why do you have to tell me to
lock up, they're going to tell me that the goats went and
did it whatever they wanted to do. So אמרי לי לגדור, amri
li ligdor, so maybe you have to put up a fence. So
מר גדירה בארעא ואי גדר, mar gedira be-ar'a ve-ee gadar, so if
you're going to tell me that you're חייב chayav to put up
a fence, so שן דחייב רחמנא היכי משכחת לה, shen de-chayav rachmana
heichi meshkachas la, so how could we ever have a case of
שן? shen? Because if the animal is always locked up, then there's
no way that the animal can escape to go into someone else's
property to cause damage of שן, shen, because...
okay, so כשחתרה, keshe-chasra, it must be in a case where it
escaped when it dug under the fence.
So... then how could you ever have a case of שן? shen?
Because if the animal escaped, then it's אונס, ones, I took all
responsibility to make sure my animal was well contained. And then the
fact that the animal broke out and and did something, so maybe
you'll tell me I'm even חייב chayav in a case where an
animal broke out, or maybe no, maybe it's only if someone damaged
the fence. Okay. So מכריז machriz רב יוסף, Rav Yosef,
this is a very interesting point. So who is, whose responsibility is
it for the fence?
In other, you know, well, that's exactly רב יוסף's Rav Yosef point.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef is very upset at these goat herds because
they own these goats, and the goats are causing damage in his
property. So he says, so they should go build a fence. And
in the end, they're going to be able to
say, look, I had a fence, I did my due.
Exactly, and what do we say הלכה, halacha, you know? I mean,
as far as I understand, this is part of the reason חז"ל
Chazal had such a, you know, throughout you'll see in בבא בתרא
Bava Batra as well, חז"ל Chazal very upset about people who grow
בהמה דקה behema daka in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because בהמה דקה,
behema daka, goats and sheep, they graze, they're going to wander onto
other people's property, they're going to eat other people's vegetables, they're going
to eat other people's fields, and it's גזל. gezel. You know, if
you are a shepherd, basically you're relying on גזל gezel to grow
your animals. So obviously you need to have a grazing policy and
laws and all sorts of things, but fundamentally at the core is
a very different kind of land use policy. So regarding that, it
sounds like it's no responsibility for the sheep owner to have to
put up a fence. They have a good claim like look, this
is, I have sheep, you know, I have my sheep and they
wander around. But then there's sort of some kind of schmutziness going
on there at least. What can I say? Okay. So מכריז machriz
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef made a declaration, ואי
תימא רבא, ve'ee teima Rava, maybe it was רבא. Rava. Okay. דסלקין
לעילא
דנחתין לתתא, desalkin le'eila denachtin letatta, so people who are going up
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or people who are coming down to
בבל, Bavel, that is he made the declaration for everybody, that is
for both type, both communities. Okay. הני עיזי דשוקא, hanei eezei deshuka,
the goats that are taken to the marketplace, דמפסדי, demapsdei,
סהדינן במריהו, sahadinan bemareyhu, they that are taken out to the marketplace
that are causing damage, I'm warning the owners, תרי ותלתא זימני, trei
utlata zimnei, and I've as if already warned the owners twice and
three times, that is to create, we're going to see a case
as if the animal is מועד muad to cause this damage.
So ציית ציית, tzayit tzayit,
ואי לא אמרינן ליה טיב אמסחתא וקבל זוזך, ve'ee lo amrinan leh
tiv amsachta vekabel zuzach, that is like
you have to go שחט shecht the animal so you got to
take care of it now. That is, he's even willing to force
the owners to שחט shecht the animals now and try to sell
them now, two days before market day when they'll get a lower
price because there's no one there to buy it, so that's going
to end up creating a situation where because they didn't control the
animals, they've lost out on their, on their profits. So this is
רב יוסף Rav Yosef taking a very strong legislative stance on this
issue, it caused him personal loss. So he, he ended up dealing
with it. Okay. The next משנה. Mishna. איזהו תם ואיזהו מועד? eizehu
tam ve'eizehu muad? Very good question. What's the difference or how does
an animal become תם tam and how does an animal become מועד?
muad? This is any animal. Yeah, any animal, but presumably we're talking
right now about a שור. shor. כל שהעידו בו שלשה ימים, kol
shehe'idu bo shlosha yamim, any animal that was testified against three days
in a row.
Or how do you get row... in a row?
Or three days, not necessarily in a row. Three days. Okay. So
that means that three days, three independent days it gored another ox.
ותם משיחזור בו שלשה ימים... vetam misheyachzor bo shlosha yamim... years apart.
That's a question as well. We're going to see that a lot
of the discussion is going to focus on רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
שיטה, shita, which is that it has to be, it could even
be three times in one day. But this is רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda שיטה. shita. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says שלשה ימים, shlosha yamim,
three days. So maybe that's why I was thinking at least in
close proximity. But it's a good question. Okay. ותם משיחזור בו שלשה
ימים, vetam misheyachzor bo shlosha yamim, and to become a תם tam
again, that is a מועד muad animal can become תם tam again
if there were three days when it didn't gore. Now what does
it mean to not gore? Not goring is obviously different than goring.
So obviously it must be a kind of not goring where there
was something that was instigating the animal and nonetheless it had some
kind of self-control or demonstrated that it wasn't in a goring mood
anymore. It can't just be totally passive. So דברי רבי יהודה, divrei
Rabbi Yehuda, that's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda שיטה. shita. רבי מאיר אומר
מועד משהעידו בו שלשה פעמים, Rabbi Meir omer muad mishehe'idu bo shlosha
pe'amim, it becomes מועד muad if it was testified against three times,
not three days. ותם כל שיהו התינוקות ממשמשין בו ואינו נוגח, vetam
kol sheyehu hatinokot memashmeshim bo ve'eino noge'ach, and to become תם tam
is if kids are playing around the ox and it does not
gore another ox. Now again, we're not talking about an ox that
gores human beings. The point is just that the children running around
playing is going to stress out the animal to the point where
it could attack and nonetheless, it did not gore, so that's proof
that it has calmed down from its goring mood.
So don't try this at home.
Don't try this at home. Well, that's it. always the suggestion. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says: מאי טעמיה דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'amei de-Rabbi
Yehuda? What is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda reasoning? Okay why does רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda think only three days? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: תמול
Temol חד, chad, מתמול mi-temol תרי, trei, שלשום shilshom תלתא telata because
the פסוק pasuk talking about the שור shor that is you can
parse the word מתמול שלשום mi-temol shilshom two and three days or
tomorrow and the next day really. תמול Temol means already one day
and then מתמול mi-temol the fact that it's not just תמול temol
but it's מתמול mi-temol is a second day. שלשום Shilshom is a
third day. It's interesting just to note שלשום shilshom I even got
caught up on it שלשום shilshom means the third day from today
which really means just two days right? It's the day after tomorrow
day before yesterday is
שלשום. shilshom. Okay so תלתא telata so that's three days. ולא ישמרנו
בעליו Ve-lo yishmerenu ba'alav and the owner did not watch it. אתאן
לנגיחה רביעית Atan le-negicha revi'it and therefore that comes to teach that
the fourth time it gores is מועד muad that is the first
three times needed to be announced to the owner and the fourth
time is already מועד. muad. So רבא אמר: Rava amar: תמול מתמול
חד. temol mi-temol chad. So he only learns תמול מתמול temol mi-temol
is one שלשום תרי. shilshom trei. ולא ישמרנו Ve-lo yishmerenu and if
you didn't guard it השתא חייב hashta chayav now you become חייב
chayav that is המחלוקת ha-machloket between אביי Abaye and רבא Rava whether
you become חייב chayav as a מועד muad on the third time
or after the third time. It seems like.
Okay so that's interesting point to note. That is when we talk
about all these kinds of חזקה chazaka and things that kick in
after three times is it third time inclusive or is it really
mean it kicks in on the fourth time after you've done it
three times? Okay so ורבי מאיר מאי טעמיה? ve-Rabbi Meir mai ta'amei?
So what's the reason for רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
So the point just for רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point is that
it has to be three independent days. That's the point. That is
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learned from the פסוק pasuk okay one day
two days three days. It's not about the number of times that
the ox has attacked it has to be the number of days.
Now you can think about it in the sense that it's isolated
incidents. That is each individual day the ox has a certain mood
is in a certain environment and that's the reason why it could
be overreacting. So even if the ox gored fifteen times in one
day according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that wouldn't be enough to
make it מועד muad because that was just one isolated bad day.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has to explain why he would say
חייב. chayav. So רבי מאיר מאי טעמיה? Rabbi Meir mai ta'amei? דתניא
De-tanya אמר רבי מאיר amar Rabbi Meir ריחק נגיחותיו חייב. richak negichotav
chayav. If he separated the gorings he's חייב. chayav. That is רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir admits agrees to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if it
was on multiple days then obviously he's חייב. chayav. קירב נגיחותיו Kirav
negichotav if they got even closer together that is if they were
tightly spaced לא כל שכן? lo kol she-ken? Isn't that a קל
וחומר? kal va-chomer? Because if they happened closer together obviously it's much
more of a מועד muad animal. It's like Michael was saying if
it was three times spread out over a month or over a
year and you're going to tell me חייב chayav obviously if it
gored all at once he should be חייב. chayav. אמרו לו Amru
lo זבה תוכיח. zava tochiach. זבה Zava is going to be a
proof against you. שריחקה ראיותיה טמאה She-richaka re'iyotiah tme'ah
קירבה ראיותיה טהורה kirva re'iyotiah tehora because a זבה zava that is
a woman with an irregular menstruation if she sees the blood on
one day that is three times on one day that would not
make her a זבה. zava. זבה Zava has to be three days
in a row. So if it was on three separate days then
she would be a זבה גדולה zava gedola and has to bring
a קרבן. korban. And if it was all on one day it
wouldn't count. So אמר להן amar la-hen הרי הוא אומר harei hu
omer וזאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו. ve-zot tihyeh tum'ato be-zovo. So what about
a זב? zav? So זב zav goes by ראיות re'iyot the number
of times you see the whatever flow that the זב zav has.
תלאה הכתוב את הזב בראיות ואת הזבה בימים. Talah ha-katuv et ha-zav
bi-re'iyot ve-et ha-zava bi-yamim. So זב zav goes by the number of
experiences of that emission and that could even be on one day
three times on one day and a זבה zava has to be
three separate days. So the פסוק pasuk distinguishes between them. ומימאי דהאי
וזאת למעוטי זבה מראיות? U-mimai de-hai ve-zot le-ma'utei zava mi-re'iyot? And what
about the fact that the פסוק pasuk says the word וזאת? ve-zot?
וזאת Ve-zot as an exclusion that is to distinguish between זבה zava
which goes by days and זב zav which goes by
ראיות. re'iyot. אימא למעוטי זב מימים. Eima le-ma'utei zav mi-yamim. Why are
you going to tell me that זבה zava gets excluded from ראיות
re'iyot that it has to be three days? Why not tell me
that זב zav is excluded from days? That is to make זב
zav even more מחמיר. machmir. אמר קרא Amar kra הזב את זובו
לזכר ולנקבה. ha-zav et zovo la-zachar ve-la-nekeva. The later פסוק pasuk says
compares them as if they're equivalent that is זב zav and זבה
zava לזכר ולנקבה. la-zachar ve-la-nekeva. מקיש זכר לנקבה. Makish zachar le-nekeva. מה
נקבה בימים Ma nekeva bi-yamim just like a woman זבה zava goes
by three days in a row אף זכר בימים. af zachar bi-yamim.
And so too if a man had one ראייה re'iyah on each
of three consecutive days that would also make him a זב. zav.
ולהקיש נקבה לזכר? U-lehakish nekeva le-zachar? So couldn't we make a היקש
hekesh the exact opposite way? מה זכר בראיות אף נקבה בראיות? Ma
zachar bi-re'iyot af nekeva bi-re'iyot? And therefore a woman who has three
ראיות re'iyot on the same day would also be a זבה? zava?
האי מיעט רחמנא וזאת. Hai mi'at rachmana ve-zot. The word וזאת ve-zot
comes as an exclusion comes as a מיעוט. mi'ut. ומה ראית מסתבר
קאי בראיות... U-ma ra'ita mistaber ka'ei bi-re'iyot... ממאי ראיות קאי בראיות ממאי
ימים? mimai reiyot ka'ei b'reiyot mimai yamim? So, meaning, in which context
are you going to exclude? Are you going to base the פסוק
pasuk based on ראיות? reiyot? So that's where you're going to exclude
about ראיות, reiyot, and in the context where it's about ימים, yamim,
you'll equate them about ימים. yamim. So it's basically we make the
closer literary kind of היקש hekesh in that context. Interesting to note,
the רמב״ם Rambam says very explicitly in ספר המצוות, Sefer HaMitzvot, he
lists the קרבנות korbanot for זב zav and זבה zava as two
separate מצוות, mitzvot, but he lists the קרבן korban for מצורע metzora
as one for both a male and female מצורע. metzora. And the
רמב״ם Rambam tells you very explicitly, he says the reason why is
because זב zav and זבה zava have very different rules, like we're
seeing here, there are distinctions between them. They're not just male and
female equivalent of the same הלכה. halakha. They're actually two different הלכות.
halakhot. But מצורע, metzora, the laws apply one hundred percent equally between
men and women, so therefore there's no
distinction. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. איזהו מועד? Eizehu mu'ad? כל שהעידו בו
שלשה ימים. Kol she-hidu bo shlosha yamim. ותם שיהיו התינוקות ממשמשין בו
ואינו נוגח. Vetam she-yihyu hatinokot mishamshanim bo ve-eino noge'ach. דברי רבי יוסי.
Divrei Rabbi Yose. Ah, so the opinion of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
is like a combination. His רישא reisha is like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, but the סיפא seifa is like
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, מועד כל
שהעידו בו שלשה פעמים ולא אמרו שלשה ימים.
mu'ad kol she-hidu bo shlosha pe'amim
velo amru shlosha yamim. אלא לחזרה בלבד. Ella l'chazara bilvad. And רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon has a different שיטה. shita. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says that it goes by שלשה פעמים, shlosha pe'amim, three times, that
is like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
but he only said that for חזרה, chazara, that's only for going
back to become a תם tam but not for מועד. mu'ad. He
has different rules for מועד mu'ad and תם. tam. It's if it
was three times in the same day, it would get you back
to תם tam according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ואמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה Ve'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha הלכה
כרבי יהודה במועד halakha k'Rabbi Yehuda bemu'ad שהרי רבי יוסי מודה לו.
sheharei Rabbi Yose modeh lo. So it's two against one about רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's שיטה shita because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose agree it has to be three different days. והלכה
כרבי מאיר בתם, Vehalakha k'Rabbi Meir betam, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is the הלכה halakha for תם, tam, why? שהרי רבי יוסי מודה
לו, Sheharei Rabbi Yose modeh lo, that if the children playing with
it is proof enough that the animal is not going to be
a מועד mu'ad anymore. And that is according to רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir's שיטה shita because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees with רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir in the law of תם. tam. So therefore we split
the difference. We basically we're פוסק paskening like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
That is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, why? Because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
gets רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda on one שיטה shita and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir on the other, so it's always two against one. אמר
ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman, so רבא Rava
disagrees, ולימא מר הלכה כרבי מאיר במועד ve-leima mar halakha k'Rabbi Meir
bemu'ad שהרי רבי שמעון מודה לו? sheharei Rabbi Shimon modeh lo? So
why can't you say oh, but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees with
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir for מועד mu'ad as well, so then it's
two against two. והלכה כרבי יהודה בתם שהרי רבי שמעון מודה לו,
Vehalakha k'Rabbi Yehuda betam sheharei Rabbi Shimon modeh lo, and maybe הלכה
halakha should be like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda בתם betam שהרי רבי
שמעון מודה לו, sheharei Rabbi Shimon modeh lo, opposite direction. So what
are you going to tell me? אמר ליה אנא כרבי יוסי סבירא
לי. Amar lei ana k'Rabbi Yose sevira li. I, that is רב
נחמן, Rav Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman wants to פוסק pasken like
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, why? דרבי יוסי נימוקו עמו. De-Rabbi Yose nimuko
imo. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose always has very good arguments. So רבי
יוסי's Rabbi Yose's שיטה shita is the one who's the best fleshed
out or something. Presumably the argument is that רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
if we can, we should פוסק pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
And this goes into a whole question of כללי הפסק. klalei hapsak.
It's interesting to note almost the opposite thing about רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir very often has חז״ל Chazal understand him
to be so brilliant that he had incredibly complex arguments for his
שיטות, shitot, that is they were very, very sophisticated and very well
argued, but they were too complicated for his colleagues to understand sometimes.
He was so innovative or so creative, it made it too hard
for people to agree with him because even if he had a
good argument, nobody else could understand it. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was almost too smart for his own good.
But we say הלכה halakha like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
That's רב נחמן's Rav Nachman's point. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says הלכה
halakha should be like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
No, but before you said oh, הלכה halakha like this and הלכה
halakha like that and הלכה halakha like the other...
Right, because the משנה Mishna was only מחלוקת machloket between רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. The fact that the ברייתא
Baraita turns out to quote רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon on the same thing and they each have a mix
and match between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is...
but we're really trying to ground the פסק psak in the משנה.
Mishna. So how does רב נחמן Rav Nachman say we פוסק pasken
like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, that is, we פוסק pasken like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in מועד mu'ad and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in
תם. tam. Okay. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, שלשה ימים
דקתני shlosha yamim dekattani לאיעודי תורא או לאיעודי גברא? l'i'udei tora o
l'i'udei gavra? So I have a question. When we talk about the
three days that you have to warn, that is we פוסק pasken
already like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so now those three days, is
that לאיעודי תורא l'i'udei tora to single out or to testify against
the ox, או לאיעודי גברא, o l'i'udei gavra, or is it
to inform the person?
I don't know what you mean by that.
In other words, is it... so this is going to be the
נפקא מינה, nafka mina, the גמרא Gemara says. למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai
nafka mina? דאתו תלתא כיתי סהדי בחד יומא. De-atu tlata kitei sahedei
be-chad yoma. That is...
the person is not מועד mu'ad of damaging.
The person is not מועד, mu'ad, correct. The animal's מועד. mu'ad. But
is the process of becoming מועד mu'ad that people saw the ox
gore and came to court and testified, or is the process that
the owner was informed that his animal had damaged another animal and
the owner didn't do anything? Is it a status of the animal,
or is it the liability on the owner? So what's the נפקא
מינה? nafka mina?
Well, doesn't it so we have that in the פסוק? pasuk? ושור
נגח הוא מתמול שלשום והועד בבעליו. ve-shor nagach hu mi-tmol shilshom ve-hu'ad
b'v'alav. Okay. והועד בבעליו.
vehu'ad b'v'alav. So we're trying to... okay. והועד בבעליו. vehu'ad b'v'alav. So
we're trying to understand, is that לאיעודי תורא? le'iudei tora? Is that
about warning the animal as if? That is, make sure that this
animal achieves a certain status after three times. It's not anything about
about
the owner's responsibility to watch the animal or not. It's just this
animal did something three times, so now it's מועד muad for that.
That means it has a חזקה chazaka of doing that. Or is
it about informing the owner and each time the owner doesn't act
on that information, the owner becomes liable.
ולו ישמרנו, velo yishmerennu, which means if he didn't...
okay, so but this is how תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be-al peh
works, we have to ask this question. So what's the נפקא מינה?
nafka mina? The point is to isolate נפקא מינה nafka mina because
נפקא מינה nafka mina is going to tell us what the question
was because it seems like people had a difficulty understanding the question.
The question is לאיעודי תורא או לאיעודי גברא? le'iudei tora o le'iudei
gavra? ומה נפקא מינה? u'mah nafka mina? דאתו תלתא כיתי סהדי בחד
יומא. de'atu tlata kitei sahedi be-chad yoma. If three groups of witnesses
come against the same ox on the same day. That is what?
That is, the owner will be able to say, yeah, I only
just heard about it, I haven't had a chance to act on
it yet. So because it was so soon, three groups, that is,
the ox gored another ox three times in the same day, the
owner will still be able to claim, yeah, I just heard about
it, I haven't had a chance to do anything yet. And that's
why the, so that would be לאיעודי תורא, le'iudei tora, that is,
three times people testified about this ox that it has a certain
status. Even though the owner has not yet had a chance to
act on it based on information of three times information, it really
was only one time to inform him because it was so fast.
Okay? אי אמרת לאיעודי תורא מיעד. ee amrat le'iudei tora mi'ad. If
you say it's about לאיעודי תורא, le'iudei tora, so the ox was
testified against. ואי אמרת לאיעודי גברא לא מיעד. ve-ee amrat le'iudei gavra
lo mi'ad. So because the owner did not get that information with
enough time to act on it. דאמר איהו השתא הוא דקמסהדי בי.
d'amar ihu hashta hu d'kamsa'adi bi. So that now is where because
he'll always be able to say that this is when you're telling,
this is when the witnesses came, so this is only now that
I'm finding out about it. So so okay, מה תא שמע? mah
ta shema? What is come teach, אין השור נעשה מועד עד שיעידו
בו בפני בעלים ובפני בית דין. ein ha-shor na'aseh mu'ad ad she-ya'idu
bo bifnei be'alim u-vifnei beit din. That the ox cannot become a
מועד mu'ad until the witnesses come and testify both in the presence
of the owner of the ox and in court. העידו בו בפני
בית דין ושלא בפני בעלים בפני בעלים ושלא בפני בית דין אינו
נעשה מועד עד שיעידו בו בפני בית דין ובפני בעלים. he'idu bo
bifnei beit din ve-she-lo bifnei be'alim bifnei be'alim ve-she-lo bifnei beit din
eino na'aseh mu'ad ad she-ya'idu bo bifnei beit din u-vifnei be'alim. It's
very long-winded. So it has to be, if it was only in
court but without the owner, or only with the owner but not
in court, it doesn't count to make the animal
מועד. mu'ad. Okay. העידו בו שנים בראשונה ושנים בשנייה ושנים בשלישית. he'idu
bo shenayim ba-rishonah u-shenayim ba-shniyah u-shenayim ba-shlishit. What if six different witnesses
came in each of three different groups? That is, two people came
the first group, and then two more came the second time, and
two more the third time, three different groups of witnesses, six people
total altogether. הרי
כאן שלוש עדויות והן עדות אחת להזמה. harei kan shalosh eduyot ve-hen
edut achat la-hazamah. It counts as three different groups of עדים. edim.
That is, if one of them is found to be a פסול
pasul witness, it only פסל pasel that group of witnesses, but the
other two would still stand. But in terms of הזמה, hazamah, in
terms of עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, it counts as one big group.
Because to achieve the status of מועד mu'ad requires three acts of
testimony. That is, they're trying to make this person now חייב chayav
in the future to pay נזק שלם nezek shalem rather than חצי
נזק. chatzi nezek. So it's a monetary case of עדים זוממים, edim
zomemim, and it's עדות אחת להזמה. edut achat la-hazamah. It counts as
one group because even if one of those witnesses was disqualified by
הזמה, hazamah, then it would break the whole status of מועד mu'ad
because you need all three testimonies. נמצאת כת ראשונה זוממת הרי כאן
שתי עדויות והוא פטור והן פטורים. nimtzeit kat rishonah zomemet harei kan
shtei eduyot ve-hu patur ve-hen pturim. If the first כת kat was
found to be עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, it's only two two groups
of witnesses, and he's פטור patur and they're פטורים. pturim. So then
you should say fine, so then each of them can, so this
is now challenging what the ברייתא braita has just said because it
says look, if you have עדים זוממים edim zomemim here, so they'll
say we didn't know about that, that we're not in collusion with
them. So can't we say that we should be פטור? patur? נמצאת
כת שנייה זוממת הרי כאן עדות אחת והוא פטור והן פטורים. nimtzeit
kat shniyah zomemet harei kan edut achat ve-hu patur ve-hen pturim. If
the second one is is עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, הרי כאן עדות
אחת. harei kan edut achat. The first group was still a good
testimony, right, because they didn't know about it, והוא פטור והן פטורים,
ve-hu patur ve-hen pturim, and then the second group should be פטור
patur because they didn't really achieve
anything, and
they're פטורים. pturim. נמצאת כת שלישית זוממת כולן חייבים. nimtzeit kat shlishit
zomemet kulan chayavim. It must be when the third group is found
to be זוממת. zomemet. That is, the first two groups of witnesses
had come with no legal result yet, and then the third group
comes to make to make the ox מועד, mu'ad, and that's the
point at which the הזמה hazamah took place. So that's the case
where someone would be חייב chayav to pay the חצי נזק, chatzi
nezek, provided the עדים זוממים edim zomemim have to pay back the
monetary costs that they tried to impose on someone else.
So wait, the עדים זוממים edim zomemim pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek
or...
no, it sounds like, it sounds like here, so that's the distinction.
That is, the first ברייתא Braisa sounded like it was עדות אחת
להזמה. Edus Achas Lahazamah. It sounds like it counts as one big
group of six witnesses for הזמה, Hazamah, and therefore they would all
six have to split it up evenly. But then the גמרא'ס שקלא
וטריא Gemara's shakla vetarya seems to come to the conclusion that it
doesn't make sense, because each of them can always say if it
was the first or second group of witnesses, they say we didn't
do anything, it wasn't our fault, without us there's no מועד, Muad,
and therefore we came first. So it's only if the third group
comes, but then they're the ones who are solely responsible for creating
the status of מועד Muad because there were only other two groups
of witnesses anyway. So they're solely responsible, so then the other four
witnesses shouldn't have to pay, it should be only those two. ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם, Va'asisem lo ka'asher zamam, you have to do to
them what they tried to do. That is to make them pay
the resultant חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek additional on top of חצי נזק.
Chatzi Nezek. That is again, if we're thinking about חצי נזק Chatzi
Nezek and חצי נזק, Chatzi Nezek, right? If we say חצי נזק
ממונא הוא, Chatzi Nezek mamona hu, it makes more sense because then
נזק שלם Nezek Shalem is ממון, Mamon, חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek is
ממון, Mamon, and the bump up from חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek to
נזק שלם Nezek Shalem is just a quantitative difference. But if they
would have to pay the full נזק שלם, Nezek Shalem, that means
qualitatively there's been a shift from שור תם Shor Tam to שור
מועד, Shor Muad, the difference between חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek and נזק
שלם Nezek Shalem that the עדים זוממים Edim Zomemim would actually have
to split the נזק שלם, Nezek Shalem, which doesn't seem to fit
the way the גמרא Gemara is talking about it, but it's an
interesting, it could be a נפקא מינה Nafka Mina for that מחלוקת
Machlokes we already had. ואי אמרת ליעודי תורא, Ve'i amarta ley'udei tora,
now this was all brought in to challenge the notion of יעודי
תורא. Iy'udei Tora. That is, if you wanted to say that it's
all about the ox achieving a certain status and has nothing to
do with the owner having been informed and being able to act
on it. ואי אמרת ליעודי תורא שפיר, Ve'i amarta ley'udei tora shapir,
it makes sense. Because why? Because the three groups of witnesses independently
almost create the status of מועד Muad without the owner having to
do anything. That is, these witnesses came to court, the owner was
there, but it's not anything about the owner being informed. ואי אמרת
ליעודי גברא, Ve'i amarta ley'udei gavra, if you say it's about the
owner actually having been informed and having time to correct that thing
and has to be three separate days. So למרו הנהו קמאי אנן
מי הוה ידעינן דבתר שלושה יומי אתו הני. Lemru hanach kamai anan
mi hava yadainan de'basar shlosha yomei asu hanei. So the first group
of witnesses will always be able to say, we didn't know that
more people were going to come and testify about this ox, we
just showed up, we saw that there was an ox and we
came and testified, so we shouldn't be included in the עדים זוממים.
Edim Zomemim. Okay, ומעידין ליה. U'me'idin lei. So
אמר רב אשי אמרתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא, Amar Rav Ashi amirtah
lishme'ata kamei de'Rav Kahana, I told this ברייתא Braisa to רב כהנא.
Rav Kahana. דאמר לי ליעודי תורא מי ניחא, De'amar li ley'udei tora
mi nicha, how can you say this fits with the notion that
it's
יעודי תורא? Iy'udei Tora? ויאמרו הנהו בתראי אנן מנא ידעינן דכל דקאי
בבי דינא לאסהודי בתורא קא אתו? Veyomru hanach basrai anan mana yadainan
dechol dekay be'vei dina le'ashudei betora ka asu? So what, you're going
to tell me that the last group of witnesses can show up
and say like we didn't know that all these other people had
come to court and testified about this ox? קא אתו אנן לחיובי
גברא פלגא נזקא אתינן. Ka asu anan lechayuvei gavra palga nizka asinan.
We just came to tell the court about one time that the
ox had gored and we thought we were making him חייב Chayav
in חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek because we didn't know about any of
the other, meaning it's not public knowledge whether this ox has two
strikes or not. So these witnesses saw an ox gore another ox,
so they said okay, so we have to go testify about that
because he's going to have to pay חצי נזק, Chatzi Nezek, it's
a שור תם. Shor Tam. And then boom, they get to court
and the court tells them, oh by the way now the ox
is a שור מועד, Shor Muad, they're going to say we didn't
even know. Meaning even the last group of witnesses is unaware of
what has gone on beforehand, and therefore how can it be ליעודי
תורא Ley'udei Tora at all according to רב כהנא? Rav Kahana? Okay,
דכל דקאי דאתו בתורא קא אתינן אנן לחיובי גברא פלגא נזקא אתינן
דקאמרי. Dechol dekay de'asu betora ka asu anan lechayuvei gavra palga nizka
asinan dekamrei. So okay, so I have a
question on this point, in other words we say like there's like
goring and then there's like real damages,
goring kills the animal.
No no no, but I'm saying like I mean did he have
to
like, kill, did the ox have to like kill an animal three
times? Or for instance, like they get into a little fight, gores
a little like, a little flesh wound.
It sounds like it has to be a real case where you
would be חייב חצי נזק, Chayav Chatzi Nezek, and חצי נזק Chatzi
Nezek sounds like קרן, Keren, קרן Keren sounds like, not sure. Does
קרן Keren if it injured the other ox
but it went to the vet and it's going to be okay,
is that the same thing? Yeah, I mean there there's still נזק,
Nezek, you still have to pay the damage, you still have to
pay the veterinarian bill, I would feel. Right, no, but I'm saying
do the three cases have to be the same? Does that make
it מועד? Muad? I don't know, that's a good question. Right, could
it be מועד Muad for נגיחה Negichah but not מועד Muad for
מיתה? Mitah? It may come up in the גמרא Gemara somewhere else,
I'm not sure. I haven't really ever learned בבא קמא Bava Kamma
so in depth to be able to answer the question well, but
it's a good question. Okay, so then what case then according to
רב כהנא Rav Kahana who says even the last witnesses who show
up have a defense against the claim that they they would have
known that they're making him שור מועד Shor Muad and therefore they'd
be part of the עדים זוממים? Edim Zomemim? So how could we
have a case of all six witnesses would be עדים זוממים? Edim
Zomemim? It must be דקמזי רמוזי, De'kamrazi remuzei, it must be where
they were winking at each other the whole
time. The problem is how do you prove that, or how do
you come to a case where there's enough evidence to actually make
them חייב chayav to pay such a case?
And also is it gores an ox? Like let's say it gores
an ox and then it gores a dog and then it gores
a...
okay, that's another good question. That is do we care about the
ניזק nizak or do we care about the מזיק? mazik? I don't
have an answer for that. רב אשי אמר כשבאו רצופים. Rav Ashi
amar k'sheba'u retzufim. רב אשי Rav Ashi has a different answer: they
came one right after another, צ'יק צ'אק. chick-chock. So that's also an
indication that these are all people coming with a conspiracy and it's
not testifying about independent cases. רבינא אמר במכירין בעל השור ואין מכירין
את השור. Ravina amar b'makirin ba'al hashor v'ein makirin et hashor. The
other proof that they're עדים זוממים edim zomemin is that they know
the owner, but they don't actually know which ox it was. What
did they do? They came and said, "Yo, פלוני, Ploni, I saw
your ox gore someone else." But if they had to go in
a lineup and pick that שור shor out of all of his
different cattle, they wouldn't be able to identify which שור shor it
was. Obviously another proof that they're in a conspiracy. אלא היכי מיעדעי
ליה? Ela heichi meiad'ei leh? So how have they informed him? דאמרי
תורא נגחא אית לך בבקרך, D'amrei tora nagcha itla b'bakarcha, because they
said, "Oh, you have a goring ox in your cattle." But they
weren't able to identify which one it was. איבעיא להו נטריה לכולי
בקרא. Iba'ya l'hu natreih l'khulei bakra. So that is we can set
this up in such a way. איבעיא להו המשיסה כלבו של חבירו
בחבירו מהו. Iba'ya l'hu hamshaseh kalbo shel chaveiro b'chaveiro mahu. So the
case is going back to the dog case now a little bit.
So in the case where the dog... he sicked his friend's dog
on someone else. So מהו? mahu? משיסה וודאי פטור. Mashseh vadai patur.
So the one who incited the dog to bite is פטור. patur.
בעל כלב, Ba'al kelev, so what about the owner of the dog?
So מאי? mai? מי אמרינן מצי אמר ליה אנא מאי עבידנא ליה?
Mi amrinan matzei amar leh ana mai avidna leh? So are you
going to tell me like, "What? I didn't do anything. I'm the
owner of the dog, I didn't do anything." So could you say
that? או דילמא אמרינן ליה כיון דידעת בכלבך דמשיסה ליה, O dilma
amrinan leh keivan d'yadata b'kalbach d'mashseh leh, you know that somebody else
has been inciting your dog to attack people,
ומשתסה, u'mishtaseh, and the dog did bite someone. So
לא איבעי לך לאשהויי, lo iba lach l'ashuyei, you shouldn't have kept
him around. That is you should have ensured that the dog would
be under better protection. אמר רבי זירא תא שמע בתם שהיו תינוקות
משמשים בו ואינו נוגח. Amar Rebbe Zeira tashma b'tam she'hayu tinokos m'shamshin
bo v'eino nogei'ach. So what does it mean to become a תם
tam again? We saw from רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir position it means
that the kids can be running around making a lot of noise
and the ox is not going to get stressed out and go
and gore something. הא נוגח חייב. Ha nogei'ach chayav. If it did
gore, then this is already a שור מועד shor mu'ad and the
kids were running around and that incites the animal to gore. So
that means that משיסה כלבו של חבירו, mashseh kalbo shel chaveiro, that
is the kids were running around and made the ox gore and
the ox did go and gore and it's a שור מועד. shor
mu'ad. So then obviously you'd be חייב נזק שלם. chayav nezek shaleim.
So here too if you incited the dog to go and bite
someone, that would also be a case of inciting. The inciter would
be חייב. chayav. אמר אביי מי קתני נגח חייב? Amar Abaye mikitani
nagach chayav? Did you say that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
never said that if the ox goes and gores that he's חייב?
chayav? All he said is that if it didn't go three times
then that means it goes back to being a תם. tam. דילמא
הא נגח לא
הוי תם.
Dilma ha
nagach lo havi tam. So just say, "Oh, maybe the possibility is
different. No, if it goes and gores, it just means that it's
not going to become a תם tam again, still מועד, mu'ad, ובהאי
נגיחה לא מחייב. u'bhahi negicha lo mechayev. But for that act of
goring is not חייב chayav because it was incited by someone else.
In other words, you can't prove one way or the other about
the dog case from the ox case. תא שמע. Tashma. Okay, שיסה
בו את הכלב שיסה בו נחש פטור. shiseh bo es hakelev shiseh
bo nachash patur. If you incited the dog to bite or the
snake to bite, you're פטור. patur. So מאי לאו? mai lav? So
why would you think... פטור משיסה וחייב בעל הכלב? patur mashseh v'chayav
ba'al hakelev? I might think the inciter is פטור patur but the
owner of the animal should be חייב. chayav. לא אימא פטור אף
משיסה, Lo eima פטור אף משיסה, and we should say no, maybe
we can say the opposite, that the owner for sure is פטור
patur and even the inciter is
פטור. patur. אמר רבא אם תמצי לומר המשיסה כלבו של חבירו בחבירו
חייב,
Amar Rava im timtzi lomar hamshaseh kalbo
shel chaveiro b'chaveiro chayav, שיסהו הוא בעצמו פטור. shisheihu hu b'atzmo patur.
If you incite the animal of someone else's animal to bite, you're
חייב, chayav, but if you incited your own animal to bite... oh
no, sorry, if you incite the dog to bite you, then פטור,
patur, that is the dog owner is פטור patur because you were
the one who was responsible, you caused yourself to be in a
situation of danger. מאי טעמא כל המשנה ובא אחר ושינה בו פטור.
Mai ta'ama kol hamshaneh u'ba acher v'shinah bo patur. If someone changed
something and then someone else comes and changed something else, פטור. patur.
What does that mean? That means in this case about the dog.
That is what did you do? You started trying to incite the
dog to attack, and then someone else came and did something else,
then פטור. patur. That is once you change something, the owner isn't
responsible anymore because it's a different circumstance.
So I'm just trying to understand, so getting back to the מועד,
mu'ad, you have to recognize which ox or not?
The point is that if the witnesses only know... knew that it
was Michael, it was one of your oxen went and gored someone.
So in that situation we're going to be more suspicious about עדים
זוממים edim zomemim type of situations.
Right, let's say they're not, let's say we can't prove they're zomemim.
Do I have to wash my entire herd because I may have
three separate
oxen? Am I liable to pay full damages if each one was
done by a different ox?
That's a good question. That's but that's what it sounds like ליעודי
גברא, le’udey gavra, right? If the owner was warned you have a
dangerous situation, you have to deal with it and it was three
times, sounds like it would apply if it was not any specific
animal, then it would have to be the whole herd. That's what
it sounds like.
So you could do that.
And the witnesses could even come and make your whole herd of
cows מועד muad if they were real witnesses.
I'm a mass produce... you know, I have like... I'm an ox
herder and I have 10,000 oxen.
And you can't identify which one was the מועד, muad, you're going
to have to watch them. You have to put up a fence,
you have to keep them on, you know, get out of that
business.
What
was he saying if somebody incites an animal to attack, neither the
owner or the inciter is liable?
That's the second opinion in the way the ברייתא braita is presented
here. It seems to be a bit of a two different ways
to read that ברייתא braita because the ברייתא braita says שיסה בו
את הכלב שיסה בו נחש פטור. shisa bo et hakelev shisa bo
nachash patur. So we said how can you read that פטור? patur?
Is it אף משסה פטור af mshase patur that the inciter is
פטור patur and certainly the owner? Or is it the משסה mshase
is פטור patur but the owner is חייב? chayav? And that has
to go partially with the question of how does a snake bite?
That is if it's really the owner's responsibility or not. But it's
two ways to read that ברייתא. braita. I don't know the way
the פסק psak comes out, I didn't check.
What's this to prevent somebody from doing this?
Meaning if someone else is coming into my property to incite my
animal to attack,
presumably at least the second opinion is how we should פסקן, pasken,
which sounds like it should be that I'm not responsible if someone
else came and riled up my animal. But the inciter is פטור
patur as well because it's not his animal.
Right. So I mean so what's going to... there's no law to
prevent somebody to do this, right? That's what I'm saying. I could
go around inciting animals.
There's a separate question of whether the law can prevent it and
whether I'm liable to pay full damages in under what circumstances. Again,
if you're trying to take my money away you have to have
a very strong claim. Whether or not what you did was אסור
assur or whether or not what you did was ethical is the
next step. But to be able to actually charge someone money in
court and to be able to extract damages is a bigger question.
Okay. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא: amar lei Rav Papa l'Rava: דאיתמר
משמיה דריש לקיש, de-itmar mishmei de-Reish Lakish, we have a מימרא memra
from ריש לקיש Reish Lakish כוותך kvatach דאמר ריש לקיש: de-amar Reish
Lakish: שתי פרות ברשות הרבים, shtei parot birshut harabim, there are two
cows in the public thoroughfare, אחת רבוצה ואחת מהלכת, achat revutza ve-achat
mahalechet, one was jumping around and one was just walking nicely. ובעטה
מהלכת ברבוצה u-va’ata mahalechet bi-revutza and the walking one...
sorry, is it like some jumping around ברבוצה bi-revutza is it like
just staying there, right? Is that רבוצה תחת משאו?
revutza tachat masa’o?
What do you mean it's jumping around?
Crouching, oh, crouching, okay, never mind, sorry, I'm sorry I got it
flipped, okay, רבוצה. revutza. So one is sitting down and one is
walking. ובעטה מהלכת ברבוצה u-va’ata mahalechet bi-revutza and the walking one, sorry,
right, the walking one kicks the one who is sitting down, פטורה,
ptura,
פטורה. ptura. Then the cow is פטור, patur, why? Because they're in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, it's רגל, regel, it's like you're walking through
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, it's totally the normal way. But רבוצה במהלכת,
revutza be-mahalechet, but what if the sitting down one kicked the one
who was walking? חייבת. chayavet. Why? Because it did something different. That
was כל המשנה, kol ha-meshane, then he's חייב. chayav. Okay? So אמר
ליה: amar lei: אנא בהאי חיובא מחייבנא. ana be-hai chiyuva mechayevna. I
would have said that you're חייב. chayav. Why? דאמרי ליה: de-amri lei:
כי אית לך רשותא לסגויי עלי למיבעט בי לית לך רשותא.
ki it lach reshuta lisgu’ei alai limva’at bi
leit lach reshuta. So you have rights to be walking through the
street but not to be kicking people. In other words, even the
one who was walking should be חייב chayav according to... according to
who is it...
רבא. Rava. Because because why? Because רבא Rava says fine, you want
to tell me that kicking is part of the normal process there,
but to kick someone, we said, is a תולדה tolada of קרן,
keren, it's not a תולדה tolada of רגל regel because kicking is
not the normal way that the cow is walking through the street.
מהלכת, mahalechet, you have the rights to be walking through the street,
you don't have rights to go kick people, to go kick other
cows. Okay, see if we can get a start a little bit
on the next משנה mishna and then we'll go from there, we'll
see how much time we have left. Okay. Next משנה mishna says:
שור המזיק ברשות הניזק. shor ha-mazik birshut ha-nizak. The שור shor that
causes damage in the property of the ניזק, nizak, that is, in
the... the שור shor of the מזיק mazik wandered into someone else's
property and caused damage. So כיצד? keitzad?
נגח נגף נשך רבץ בעט ברשות הרבים. nagach nagaph nashach ravatz ba’at
birshut harabim. So the ox gored
or... there's different kinds of goring... or bit someone or
sat on something or kicked something in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, משלם
חצי נזק. meshalem chatzi nezek. ברשות הניזק רבי טרפון אומר נזק שלם
וחכמים אומרים חצי נזק. birshut ha-nizak Rebbe Tarfon omer nezek shalem va-chachamim
omrim chatzi nezek. So in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, this is a
מחלוקת machloket we already saw. So רשות הרבים reshut harabim we know
you pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek for a תם tam because that's
the rule. In רשות הניזק reshut hanizak what if it wandered into
someone else's yard and caused damage? So then it's going to be
a מחלוקת. machloket. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says נזק שלם nezek shaleim
because the special פטור p'tor of חצי נזק chatzi nezek doesn't apply
anymore. The תורה Torah only made you פטור patur to only pay
חצי נזק chatzi nezek in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim because there's a
certain notion that you have rights to be going there. If you're
going into somebody else's property, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is going to
say you don't have those rights anymore. But חכמים אומרים חצי נזק.
chachamim omrim chatzi nezek. And חצי נזק chatzi nezek is not some
special illogical thing, it just happens to be that's the תורה's Torah
rule for תם tam animal to cause a נזק nezek of קרן,
keren, you pay only חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. So חכמים chachamim would
apply it equally in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim or in רשות הניזק.
reshut hanizak. אמר להם רבי טרפון, amar lahem Rabbi Tarfon, רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon has to defend himself, ומה במקום שהקל על השן ועל
הרגל ברשות הרבים שהוא פטור, u-mah bimkom she-heikel al ha-shein ve-al ha-regel
bi-reshut harabbim she-hu patur, so שן shein and רגל regel are פטור
patur in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, החמיר עליהם ברשות הניזק hechmir aleihem
bi-reshut hanizak and nonetheless in the private domain you pay full נזק
nezek for שן shein and רגל, regel, לשלם נזק שלם, leshalem nezek
shaleim, מקום שהחמיר על הקרן ברשות הרבים, makom she-hechmir al ha-keren bi-reshut
harabbim, in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim you're not פטור, patur, you have
to pay נזק, nezek, חצי נזק, chatzi nezek, לשלם חצי נזק, leshalem
chatzi nezek, אינו דין שנחמיר עליו ברשות הניזק לשלם נזק שלם? eino
din she-nachmir alav bi-reshut hanizak leshalem nezek shaleim? So if it's in
רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, shouldn't we also be more מחמיר machmir and
make you pay נזק שלם? nezek shaleim? So אמרו לו דייו לבא
מן הדין להיות כנידון. amru lo dayyo la-ba min ha-din lihyot ka-nidon.
No, you have to apply the rules appropriately. מה ברשות הרבים חצי
נזק אף ברשות הניזק חצי נזק. mah bi-reshut harabbim chatzi nezek af
bi-reshut hanizak chatzi nezek. No, קרן תם keren tam pays חצי נזק.
chatzi nezek. That's the rule for חכמים. chachamim. And therefore don't try
to bring me קל וחומרס, kal vachomers, רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, it's
just the way the rules work. קרן תם keren tam pays חצי
נזק. chatzi nezek. So אמר להם אף אני לא אדון קרן מקרן.
amar lahem af ani lo adon keren mi-keren. I'm not trying to
compare קרן keren to קרן. keren. אני אדון קרן מרגל. ani adon
keren mi-regel. I'm trying to compare קרן keren to רגל. regel. In
what sense?
ומה במקום שהקל—I u-mah bimkom she-heikel like his answer though. No, because
רגל regel you're פטור patur in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and you
pay נזק שלם nezek shaleim in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. קרן תם
keren tam you pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek in רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim and according to חכמים chachamim you should pay חצי נזק chatzi
nezek also in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. So it's less חמור chamur
than רגל regel in רשות הניזק reshut hanizak and it's more חמור
chamur than רגל regel in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim according to that...
No, the חכמים chachamim would just say this. Meaning they... Right, that's
all.
That that's a מחלוקת. machloket. Right, so רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says
אני אדון קרן מרגל. ani adon keren mi-regel. I'm comparing קרן תם
keren tam to רגל regel with a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה
במקום שהקל על השן ועל הרגל ברשות הרבים החמיר בקרן מקום שהחמיר
על השן ועל הרגל ברשות הניזק אינו דין שנחמיר בקרן. u-mah bi-mkom
she-heikel al ha-shein ve-al ha-regel bi-reshut harabbim hechmir be-keren makom she-hechmir al
ha-shein ve-al ha-regel bi-reshut hanizak eino din she-nachmir be-keren.
So shouldn't we be more מחמיר machmir with קרן keren in רשות
הניזק? reshut hanizak? That is, the animal wandered into somebody else's property
and gored something or sat on something, so obviously it should be
you should pay נזק שלם nezek shaleim according to רבי טרפון. Rabbi
Tarfon. Okay, why? Okay, so אמרו לו דייו לבא מן הדין להיות
כנידון, amru lo dayyo la-ba min ha-din lihyot ka-nidon, מה ברשות הרבים
חצי נזק אף ברשות הניזק חצי נזק. mah bi-reshut harabbim chatzi nezek
af bi-reshut hanizak chatzi nezek. Stop trying to bring me קל וחומרס,
kal vachomers, רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, it's just gonna have to be
the way it is, you pay only חצי נזק. chatzi nezek.
So I guess we should pick up here because the גמרא Gemara
is a bit of a long סוגיא sugya going in. Just one
other point which is interesting to flip back, if you look on
כ"ד עמוד א', kaf daled amud aleph, there's a short תוספות Tosafot
there אי ליעודי גברא. i le-idduei gavra. So תוספות Tosafot there makes
the point that it seems like the discussion we're having is about
the התראה, hatra'ah, that is, what happened? You got warned three times
and then you become חייב chayav the fourth time. So why? Because
you
didn't—like how do you count the times that you're חייב? chayav? Is
it three times that you didn't act on having been warned?
Three strikes in a row.
But when do you count the strikes from? Is it—meaning תוספות Tosafot
says אי ליעודי גברא לא שיהא מועד לעבור בהתראות דאם כן לא
היה מחייב עד נגיחה של חמישית. i le-idduei gavra lo she-yehei muad
la-avor be-hatra'ot de-im ken lo haya mechayev ad negichah shel chamishit. Why?
Because the fourth one is also just a violation of the third
warning. Because what happened? That is, you got—you had a נגיחה, negichah,
right? These markers don't even work. Okay. You had a נגיחה negichah
and then you had התראה. hatra'ah. Then you had a נגיחה negichah
and you had התראה hatra'ah and then you had a נגיחה negichah
and you had התראה. hatra'ah. So you were warned three times. So
what happens? The fourth time you have a goring, right, that means
you've violated the warning three times. And that's what makes you חייב.
chayav. So maybe you only become חייב chayav on the fifth time
because this one is already just really your third one. This first
time just created the warning that will make you חייב chayav later.
So this תוספות Tosafot says don't think that because it's not about
התראה, hatra'ah, it's not about warning, it's actually about the act of
goring. התראה hatra'ah is as if or the—is not warning like you
have with normal crimes or other kinds of situations. It's really just
creating a status based on the times that it gored. So the
מועד muad status is not about having violated the warning but is
about the status, and that goes back to that מחלוקת machloket about
whether it is ליעודי גברא או ליעודי תורא. le-idduei gavra o le-idduei
tora. That is, this fits much better—the way תוספות Tosafot explains the
סוגיא sugya fits much better with ליעודי תורא. le-idduei tora. That is,
it's a status that the ox has acquired. It's not about whether
or not the person has violated their liability—their responsibility or not to
be informed about what this animal is capable of. Interestingly enough, another
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, contradicts exactly this
and says exactly the conclusion that this תוספות Tosafot rejects, that is...
Because you really only become חייב Chayav on the fifth time because
the fourth time is still part of the first cluster, because really
is about violating that התראה, Hatra'ah, that warning. So just an interesting
point that the two different approaches in תוספות Tosafot about how to
understand that notion. Okay, great.